<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2022-03-31T01:09:59+01:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Adventures in Game Development</title><subtitle>A development blog of an aspiring Game Developer, making one game a month and sharing everything he learns along the way.
</subtitle><author><name>dudezord</name><email>dudezord@protonmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Making my first game - Portcullis (Part 1)</title><link href="/blog/2022-04-01-making-my-first-game-portcullis-part-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making my first game - Portcullis (Part 1)" /><published>2022-04-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-03-31T01:08:17+01:00</updated><id>/blog/making-my-first-game-portcullis-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2022-04-01-making-my-first-game-portcullis-part-1/"><![CDATA[<ul id="markdown-toc">
  <li><a href="#greetings-fellow-adventurer" id="markdown-toc-greetings-fellow-adventurer">Greetings, fellow adventurer!</a></li>
  <li><a href="#theme---portcullis" id="markdown-toc-theme---portcullis">Theme - “Portcullis”</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#definition" id="markdown-toc-definition">Definition</a></li>
      <li><a href="#initial-ideas" id="markdown-toc-initial-ideas">Initial ideas</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#game-concept---gatekeeper" id="markdown-toc-game-concept---gatekeeper">Game Concept - “Gatekeeper”</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="greetings-fellow-adventurer">Greetings, fellow adventurer!</h2>

<p>The time has come for my first challenge.
As you <a href="/blog/2022-03-02-the-plan-is-simple/" class="external">already know</a>, I will be doing one game a month as a way to learn everything I can about game development.</p>

<p>Starting from now (April 2022), every month I will make a game from start-to-finish based on one of the original themes of <a href="/projects/1GAM">#1GAM</a>.</p>

<p>With that in mind, the theme for this month is… <em>**drum roll**</em></p>

<h2 id="theme---portcullis">Theme - “Portcullis”</h2>

<p>Before we proceed, I suggest you listen to the <a href="/projects/1GAM/#1">original keynote</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/McFunkypants">@McFunkypants</a>.<br />
His words convey all the meaning that I want this blog to have.<br />
For lots of current game developers, their journey started there and then. For me, it (re-)starts now.<br /></p>

<p>With that in mind, let’s begin!</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <h3 id="definition">Definition</h3>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portcullis">Portcullis</a> is the name given to a defensive sliding gate at the entrance of a castle. It is mounted on vertical grooves and can be raised and lowered very rapidly by a single guard. It can be used to prevent the passage of unwanted enemies, or even to trap them between two consecutive portcullises.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <h3 id="initial-ideas">Initial ideas</h3>
    <p>The first game ideas that came to my mind were:</p>
    <ul>
      <li><strong>“Gatekeeper”</strong> - You guard the main gate of your medieval city. You have to decide who enters and who can leave. Good choices might have good consequences. Bad choices will always prove to be bad.</li>
      <li><strong>“Open the gate!”</strong> - The King and Queen have returned from their long vacation, but it looks like they lost the keys to the Castle. You, as the Official Lockpicker of the Reign, shall open the gate for their Royal Highnesses. But don’t take too long, or you might lose your head.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>I decided to go with <strong>“Gatekeeper”</strong> as I was having some issues coming up with puzzles/mechanics for the other title.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="game-concept---gatekeeper">Game Concept - “Gatekeeper”</h2>
<p>In this game, you play the very important role of guarding the entrance to the city.<br />
As a core mechanic, you will have the ability of lowering and raising the Portcullis.</p>

<p>You might allow your citizens to enter, while prohibiting undesired people from doing the same.
When enemies come to attack, you will be able to use the spikes of the falling Portcullis to crush them and prevent their success.</p>

<p>Do a good enough of a job and you will be able to upgrade your abilities in defending the Kingdom.<br />
Do a bad enough of a job and it will be your head on a spike instead!</p>

<p><br />
<br />
Time to finally get my hands dirty and play with <a href="https://godotengine.org">Godot</a> for the first time.<br />
I’ll be back next week, with an update on the development of this project. See you soon!</p>]]></content><author><name>dudezord</name><email>dudezord@protonmail.com</email></author><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/01-portcullis/part-1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/01-portcullis/part-1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The plan is simple</title><link href="/blog/2022-03-02-the-plan-is-simple/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The plan is simple" /><published>2022-03-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-31T01:08:18+01:00</updated><id>/blog/the-plan-is-simple</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2022-03-02-the-plan-is-simple/"><![CDATA[<p class="note">If you haven’t read my <a href="/blog/2022-03-01-a-new-beginning">initial blog post</a>, please check it first!</p>

<ul id="markdown-toc">
  <li><a href="#the-plan-is-simple" id="markdown-toc-the-plan-is-simple">The plan is simple</a></li>
  <li><a href="#or-is-it" id="markdown-toc-or-is-it">Or is it?</a></li>
  <li><a href="#ready-set" id="markdown-toc-ready-set">Ready? Set…</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-plan-is-simple">The plan is simple</h2>

<p>I already have some definitive ideas about what I want to do:</p>
<ul>
  <li>All the programming will be done on <a href="https://godotengine.org"><strong>Godot</strong></a>. I only have a little bit of experience using other engines, but since Godot is the <em>“new”</em> cool kid on the block, I decided on it.</li>
  <li>Project ideas will come sequentially from the amazing list of <a href="/projects/1GAM"><strong>#1GAM</strong></a>. I compiled the entire list of themes and keynotes since they aren’t available on the original site anymore.</li>
  <li>On each project, I will focus on improving one or more parts of game development where I don’t feel as confident. This can be anything from planning, writing, coding, art, modelling, music, marketing, setting up a Steam page, etc. 
<br />I only ever did <strong>programming</strong> since 2008, so the opportunities to learn the remaining stuff are endless.</li>
  <li>Regarding <em>deadlines</em>, I intend to honor the <a href="/projects/1GAM"><strong>#1GAM</strong></a> motto - one game a month.</li>
  <li>Document everything! This is a learning experiment, both for you and me. Even a website/blog is something I never did in the past. We are already making progress! 😄</li>
  <li>… and most important, <strong>ENJOY</strong> the journey!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="or-is-it">Or is it?</h2>

<p>I still don’t know what software I’ll use for practicing all the other stuff. I also don’t know how frequently I should write updates on my progress.
<br />
I’ll gladly take suggestions from the audience.</p>

<h2 id="ready-set">Ready? Set…</h2>
<p>I guess we will have to see how it goes!</p>]]></content><author><name>dudezord</name><email>dudezord@protonmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If you haven’t read my initial blog post, please check it first!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/solo-developers.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/solo-developers.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A new beginning</title><link href="/blog/2022-03-01-a-new-beginning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A new beginning" /><published>2022-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-31T01:08:19+01:00</updated><id>/blog/a-new-beginning</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2022-03-01-a-new-beginning/"><![CDATA[<ul id="markdown-toc">
  <li><a href="#hello-everyone" id="markdown-toc-hello-everyone">Hello everyone!</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="hello-everyone">Hello everyone!</h2>
<p><br />
My real name is Pedro and I was born in the beautiful and sunny 🇵🇹 Portugal.
<br />
Since I was a young child that I had the desire to one day become a Game Developer.</p>

<p>At 18 years of age, I started to pursue my dream and enrolled in a Computer Science degree.
<br />
At 26 years of age, I finished my MSc in Graphics Programming and Game Development.</p>

<p>I was ready. The World was ready. The time had come. Right? <em>Right…?!?!</em></p>

<p>5 years have already passed and the answer is: <strong>WRONG</strong>!</p>

<p>I was never able to work on games professionally.
<br />
And because of that I also never had the motivation to work on them on my free time.</p>

<p>The time has finally come… The journey starts now!</p>]]></content><author><name>dudezord</name><email>dudezord@protonmail.com</email></author><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/press-start.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/press-start.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>