<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2022-06-02T18:48:25+01:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Adventures in Game Development</title><subtitle>A development blog of an aspiring Game Developer, making one game a month and sharing everything he learns along the way.
</subtitle><author><name>dudezord</name><email>dudezord@protonmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Making my third game - Rogue (Part 1)</title><link href="/blog/2022-06-01-making-my-third-game-rogue-part-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making my third game - Rogue (Part 1)" /><published>2022-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-06-02T18:47:49+01:00</updated><id>/blog/making-my-third-game-rogue-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2022-06-01-making-my-third-game-rogue-part-1/"><![CDATA[<ul id="markdown-toc">
  <li><a href="#third-time-is-the-charm" id="markdown-toc-third-time-is-the-charm">Third time is the charm!</a></li>
  <li><a href="#theme---rogue" id="markdown-toc-theme---rogue">Theme - “Rogue”</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#definition" id="markdown-toc-definition">Definition</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#game-concept---infection" id="markdown-toc-game-concept---infection">Game Concept - “Infection”</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="third-time-is-the-charm">Third time is the charm!</h2>

<p>Be very welcome to month #3. The time has arrived for a new challenge.</p>

<p>As you <a href="/blog/2022-03-02-the-plan-is-simple/" class="external">already know</a>, I’m doing one game a month as a way to learn everything I can about game development.</p>

<p>Every month I will make a game from start-to-finish based on one of the original themes of <a href="/projects/1GAM">#1GAM</a>.<br />
The final result from the previous month is here: <a href="/projects/spectrum-attack" class="external">Spectrum Attack!</a></p>

<p>And without further ado, June brings us… <em>**drum roll**</em></p>

<h2 id="theme---rogue">Theme - “Rogue”</h2>

<p>If you are interested, you can listen to the <a href="/projects/1GAM/#3">original keynote</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/McFunkypants">@McFunkypants</a>.<br /></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <h3 id="definition">Definition</h3>
    <p><a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/rogue">Rogue</a> represents everything that is mischievous or deceitful. It can range from a person, to a plant or even to a computer-virus.
In the context of video-games it is used in reference to the term <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roguelike">Roguelike</a>, which represents a subgenre of games categorized by dungeon crawling, turn-based gameplay and inventory management.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><br /></p>

<p>Starting this month, I will try to conjugate working on the game with exercising. I came up with this idea after watching <a href="https://www.twitch.tv/dev_spajus">dev_spajus</a> doing the same on his Twitch stream.</p>

<p>I bought a treadmill and created a stand from some wood planks where I can put my laptop while I walk.</p>

<p>It is already proving to be succesful because after 45min I was able to figure out what I wanted to do for this month and in another 45min I wrote this entire blog post!</p>

<h2 id="game-concept---infection">Game Concept - “Infection”</h2>

<p>A super computer-virus was created to infect the highly-advanced infrastructures of all enemies of your great Nation. You must ensure its succesfulness and aid it in its mission before being detected and traced back to your country.</p>

<p>The game will consist of elements of evasion and battle. The player will be responsible with deciding what are the next actions to take. The player will battle some computer-systems of the infrastructure by using deckbuilder mechanics, where winning a battle grants you additional cards with the strenghts of the fallen foe.</p>

<p>Alternatively, the player might choose to evade the battle in order to inspect other parts of the infrastructure which might help them on their mission.</p>

<p>In order to help being undetected, our virus makes use of a Random Number Generator to define how many action-points the player will have to battle or evade.</p>

<p><br />
<br />
<br />
I hope that this month I will have a lot more time to work on the game. Scope-wise, this will be a lot more complex than the previous game as I will need to create several cards, their unique art, balance their stats in order to make the game fun, etc.</p>

<p><br />
The plan is now laid down. Time to go to business!<br />
I’ll be back next week, with an update on the development of this project. See you soon!</p>]]></content><author><name>dudezord</name><email>dudezord@protonmail.com</email></author><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/03-rogue/part-1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/03-rogue/part-1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Making my second game - Sound (Part 2 - Finale)</title><link href="/blog/2022-05-28-making-my-second-game-sound-part-2-finale/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making my second game - Sound (Part 2 - Finale)" /><published>2022-05-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-05-28T19:05:09+01:00</updated><id>/blog/making-my-second-game-sound-part-2-finale</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2022-05-28-making-my-second-game-sound-part-2-finale/"><![CDATA[<p class="note">If you haven’t yet, please read <a href="/blog/2022-05-01-making-my-second-game-sound-part-1">Part 1</a>.</p>

<ul id="markdown-toc">
  <li><a href="#spectrum-attack-is-done" id="markdown-toc-spectrum-attack-is-done">Spectrum Attack is done!</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#the-twist-again" id="markdown-toc-the-twist-again">The Twist (again)</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#the-game" id="markdown-toc-the-game">The Game</a></li>
  <li><a href="#tasks" id="markdown-toc-tasks">Tasks</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#spectrum-analyzer" id="markdown-toc-spectrum-analyzer">Spectrum Analyzer</a></li>
      <li><a href="#falling-rain" id="markdown-toc-falling-rain">Falling Rain</a></li>
      <li><a href="#rolling-cat" id="markdown-toc-rolling-cat">Rolling Cat</a></li>
      <li><a href="#ui" id="markdown-toc-ui">UI</a></li>
      <li><a href="#art--music" id="markdown-toc-art--music">Art / Music</a></li>
      <li><a href="#thats-it-for-may" id="markdown-toc-thats-it-for-may">That’s it for May!</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="spectrum-attack-is-done">Spectrum Attack is done!</h2>

<p>The second monthly project is now over.</p>

<p>This was a rough month. So this will be the only update of the month for <strong>Spectrum Attack!</strong></p>

<h3 id="the-twist-again">The Twist (again)</h3>

<p>If you read the last devlog of April then you already know that I caught Covid-19. And it sucked… I thought it was going to be a walk in the park, because of vaccines and stuff. Oh boy, how wrong I was…</p>

<p>I ended up having symptoms for a total of four weeks, which didn’t allow me to stay at the computer for more than a couple minutes of a time, since I would get very nauseous.</p>

<p>So basically, everything related to this game was done in the last couple of days.</p>

<p>I thought about postponing this month’s project to June, but that meant to break my initial promise after only one month, so I pushed through it.</p>

<p>Overall, I think it still payed off.</p>

<h2 id="the-game">The Game</h2>

<p>I finished <a href="/blog/2022-05-01-making-my-second-game-sound-part-1">Part 1</a> being somewhat vague on what the game would be about.
I stated that the game would feature its Music as the main gameplay element and I was able to keep that promise!</p>

<p><strong>Spectrum Attack!</strong> is a game about a cat that either loves or hates rain! Roll your way around while the music plays and either grab or avoid the rain drops.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/projects/02-spectrum-attack/itch-thumbnail.png" width="50%" /></p>

<h2 id="tasks">Tasks</h2>

<h3 id="spectrum-analyzer">Spectrum Analyzer</h3>
<p>I started by implement an analyzer that would give me a histrogram of the different sound frequencies that were being played. Fortunately, this was very easy since Godot provides a very <a href="https://godotengine.org/article/godot-32-will-get-new-audio-features">easy-to-use API</a> exactly for this.</p>

<p>After having it working, I refactored it in order to give me the notes which were being played, no matter what octave it was. Basically, summing every 12nd interval in its own group.</p>

<p>Since notes being played on top of the others create lots of frequency noise, I decided accumulate these samples and only query which notes were being played a handful times per second.</p>

<h3 id="falling-rain">Falling Rain</h3>
<p>Querying the previous accumulated samples gives me numbers from 0 to 11 (A, A#, B, C, C#, D, D#, E, F, F#, G, G#).</p>

<p>I divide the screen in 12 vertical strips and then spawn rain-drops in the corresponding slot for the notes that are being played at that exact time.</p>

<h3 id="rolling-cat">Rolling Cat</h3>
<p>Now, it’s just a matter of implementing a player entity for us to control!</p>

<p>I decided on a cute cat that rolls around trying to avoid the rain.
For this, I just move it left and right and apply an adequate rotation speed.</p>

<p>Since straight-falling rain was too easy, I make sure the rain falls always in the direction where the player is, for added difficulty.</p>

<h3 id="ui">UI</h3>
<p>I came up with a very simple UI, since time was short.</p>

<p>On the main menu there are two buttons, for two different game modes: either collect the rain drops, or avoid them.</p>

<p>I have a timer to tell how much until the round ends. I also keep track of the player score and show a “damage” indicator when the score is decreased.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/blog/posts/02-sound/part-2-ui.png" width="50%" /></p>

<h3 id="art--music">Art / Music</h3>
<p>None of the art (background, cat, rain-drops) was done by me.
My contribution for this game is strictly the entire code on it.</p>

<p>I really wanted to make my own assets, but I wasn’t on a physical or mental state necessary to do it.</p>

<h3 id="thats-it-for-may">That’s it for May!</h3>

<p>May had its ups and downs, but I finished game number two!</p>

<p>Here is the project page for <a href="/projects/spectrum-attack">Spectrum Attack!</a> Give it a look and, preferably, a play!</p>

<p>I’ll see you next month!</p>]]></content><author><name>dudezord</name><email>dudezord@protonmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If you haven’t yet, please read Part 1.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/02-sound/part-2-finale.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/02-sound/part-2-finale.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Making my second game - Sound (Part 1)</title><link href="/blog/2022-05-01-making-my-second-game-sound-part-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making my second game - Sound (Part 1)" /><published>2022-05-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-05-01T18:39:31+01:00</updated><id>/blog/making-my-second-game-sound-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2022-05-01-making-my-second-game-sound-part-1/"><![CDATA[<ul id="markdown-toc">
  <li><a href="#second-month-second-challenge" id="markdown-toc-second-month-second-challenge">Second month, second challenge!</a></li>
  <li><a href="#theme---sound" id="markdown-toc-theme---sound">Theme - “Sound”</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#definition" id="markdown-toc-definition">Definition</a></li>
      <li><a href="#initial-ideas" id="markdown-toc-initial-ideas">Initial ideas</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#game-concept---spectrum-attack" id="markdown-toc-game-concept---spectrum-attack">Game Concept - “Spectrum Attack”</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="second-month-second-challenge">Second month, second challenge!</h2>

<p>Hello, everyone. Welcome to month #2!</p>

<p>As you <a href="/blog/2022-03-02-the-plan-is-simple/" class="external">already know</a>, I’m doing one game a month as a way to learn everything I can about game development.</p>

<p>Every month I will make a game from start-to-finish based on one of the original themes of <a href="/projects/1GAM">#1GAM</a>.<br />
The final result from the previous month is here: <a href="/projects/Gatekeeper" class="external">Gatekeeper</a>.</p>

<p>With that in mind, the theme for this month is… <em>**drum roll**</em></p>

<h2 id="theme---sound">Theme - “Sound”</h2>

<p>If you are interested, please listen to the <a href="/projects/1GAM/#2">original keynote</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/McFunkypants">@McFunkypants</a>.<br /></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <h3 id="definition">Definition</h3>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sound">Sound</a> is a vibration that propagates through air/water/etc. as if it were a wave. Once it reaches our ear, it is then amplified and channelled into the cochlea. The cochlea is filled with fluid that moves in response to this vibration. 25,000 nerve endings attached to the cochlea then detect this movement and transform it into electrical signals that are sent to the brain. The brain will then turn these signals into a sound that we can locate, recognize and understand.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <h3 id="initial-ideas">Initial ideas</h3>
    <p>I came with a number of ideas for this theme, but quickly discarded most of them as I wasn’t able to quickly figure out a way of turning each mechanic into a fun experience for the players. The ideas were:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        <p><strong>“Goldberg’s Tune”</strong> - You need to create your own Goldberg Machine out of preset pieces. Your challenge is to replicate a series of famous tunes while creating amazing contraptions.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p><strong>“Blind Sky”</strong> - You are a blind person experiencing an airplane flight baptism. Something goes wrong and your pilot is no longer able to fly the airplane. Your mission is to turn back and land safely, depending exclusively on your hearing and the instructions that are given from the Airport Control Tower.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p><strong>“Spectrum Attack”</strong> - The player has to survive the duration of a specific song. Each beat/tone/speed change spawns a new enemy, which the player will be able to either dodge or destroy.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>

    <p>In the end I decided on <strong>“Spectrum Attack”</strong> as it is the concept that allows for more prototyping and ability to come up with something fun.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="game-concept---spectrum-attack">Game Concept - “Spectrum Attack”</h2>

<p>In this game, the music is the most important aspect of gameplay. The characteristics of each song will determine when and where enemies spawn. Your objective is to survive the entire song, either by avoiding enemies or by destroying them.</p>

<p>The gameplay can be something like “Asteroids” where asteroids spawn “randomly” around you and you have to destroy them.<br /></p>

<p>Alternatively, it can be something like a top-down vertical bullet hell, where you have to actively avoid everything for the duration of the song.</p>

<p>I’m not yet sure on what I want to work, so I’ll have to play a little bit with prototypes and see where it takes me!
<br />
<br />
Time to go back to <a href="https://godotengine.org">Godot</a> and start exploring.<br />
I’ll be back next week, with an update on the development of this project. See you soon!</p>]]></content><author><name>dudezord</name><email>dudezord@protonmail.com</email></author><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/02-sound/part-1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/02-sound/part-1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Making my first game - Portcullis (Part 4 - Finale)</title><link href="/blog/2022-04-28-making-my-first-game-portcullis-part-4-finale/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making my first game - Portcullis (Part 4 - Finale)" /><published>2022-04-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-05-28T14:10:28+01:00</updated><id>/blog/making-my-first-game-portcullis-part-4-finale</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2022-04-28-making-my-first-game-portcullis-part-4-finale/"><![CDATA[<p class="note">If you haven’t yet, please read <a href="/blog/2022-04-01-making-my-first-game-portcullis-part-1">Part 1</a>, <a href="/blog/2022-04-09-making-my-first-game-portcullis-part-2">Part 2</a> and <a href="/blog/2022-04-19-making-my-first-game-portcullis-part-3">Part 3</a>.</p>

<ul id="markdown-toc">
  <li><a href="#we-did-it-we-finished-gatekeeper" id="markdown-toc-we-did-it-we-finished-gatekeeper">We did it, we finished Gatekeeper!</a></li>
  <li><a href="#tasks" id="markdown-toc-tasks">Tasks</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#difficulty-tweaking" id="markdown-toc-difficulty-tweaking">Difficulty Tweaking</a></li>
      <li><a href="#game-art" id="markdown-toc-game-art">Game Art</a>        <ul>
          <li><a href="#enemy--villager" id="markdown-toc-enemy--villager">Enemy / Villager</a></li>
          <li><a href="#gate--walls" id="markdown-toc-gate--walls">Gate / Walls</a></li>
          <li><a href="#ui" id="markdown-toc-ui">UI</a></li>
          <li><a href="#sound-effects--music" id="markdown-toc-sound-effects--music">Sound effects / Music</a></li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li><a href="#the-twist" id="markdown-toc-the-twist">The Twist</a></li>
      <li><a href="#thats-all-folks" id="markdown-toc-thats-all-folks">That’s all Folks!</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="we-did-it-we-finished-gatekeeper">We did it, we finished Gatekeeper!</h2>

<p>The first monthly project is now over.</p>

<p>Let me start by saying that I’m very proud of the final result. Biased, I know… It’s not the most beautiful game in the World. It also isn’t the most fun… But it is <strong>mine</strong>!</p>

<p>If you remember, last week we already had some basic <strong>Winning/Losing</strong> conditions and started working on <strong>Game Art</strong>.</p>

<p>For this week’s update, this is what I worked on:</p>

<h2 id="tasks">Tasks</h2>

<h3 id="difficulty-tweaking">Difficulty Tweaking</h3>
<p>I played a little bit with everything I mentioned on the last post. The objective was to balance the game in order to make it as engaging as possible.</p>

<p>The gate animation speeds up the higher your <strong>Morale</strong>. I created 3 different raising animations so that the speed felt adequate to each one of these animations.</p>

<p>The mobs’ walking speed is randomized increasingly as the <strong>Morale</strong> goes up. At the start of the game their walking speed is constant, but it becomes more diverse in the late game.</p>

<p>As the <strong>Morale</strong> increases, the mobs’ spawning also gets faster and more unpredictable.</p>

<p>With optimal gameplay, the player should be able to reach maximum <strong>Morale</strong> after 50 seconds of playing and then they keep the last 40 seconds of gameplay trying to decide which are the best clusters of mobs to attack and which are the bests to let through.</p>

<p>If you take too much to decide, either the bad guys will enter or your Gate will be damage by the mob of people wanting to go inside. Be quick!</p>

<h3 id="game-art">Game Art</h3>
<h4 id="enemy--villager">Enemy / Villager</h4>

<p>For the mobs, I wanted to make sure their own sprites had a walking animation. I ended up creating a very simple 4-frame animation. I actually spent very little time doing the mobs, since they are basically recolors of one-another.</p>

<p>I made a first version of the mobs to test in-game and immediately got some feedback on how they seemed to be tilting backwards. Since walking is basically “continuously falling forward” I tweaked the art a little bit and it really made a difference.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/blog/posts/01-portcullis/part-4-mobs.png" width="50%" /></p>

<h4 id="gate--walls">Gate / Walls</h4>

<p>This wasn’t original planned, but the same person that gave the feedback on the mobs’ sprites also told me that the remaining of the assets lacked some depth, since the Gate and the Walls looked like flat sheets of paper. I also thought it would be great if the spikes really penetrated the grass and made a hole. So, I added some depth to these textures and some dirt/holes where the spikes hit and now everything looks really cool!</p>

<p>Upon seeing how cool these updated textures looked, I immediately noticed that now the gate lacked some “weight” to it. So I did what everyone would do as well: I added particle effects and screen shake everytime the Gate hits the ground, for that extra feel of impact.</p>

<video controls="" src="/assets/img/blog/posts/01-portcullis/part-4-gate-walls.mp4" width="50%"></video>

<h4 id="ui">UI</h4>

<p>I ended up not doing anything on the <strong>Morale</strong> and <strong>Gate Health</strong> progress bars. Instead, I did the next best thing: I added damage sprites to the Gate, which gets more damaged as its Health decreases. This helps selling the idea that the bar above the Gate represents its health.</p>

<p>I also added an extremely simple Start/Ending screen, with a single button to Play the game and a text-field to show if you were successful or not and your score.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/blog/posts/01-portcullis/part-4-start-screen.png" width="50%" /></p>

<p>I would have loved to have prettier screens, with a Credits scene for example, but I had a very convincing reason not to do that. I explain it later.</p>

<h4 id="sound-effects--music">Sound effects / Music</h4>

<p>Since this was also a completely new topic for me, I started with some research on what software were available and which ones I would like to work it.
Upon some independent reading and some personal recommendations from GameDev people I follow, I ended up picking <a href="https://sfbgames.itch.io/chiptone">ChipTone</a> for the sound-effects and <a href="https://www.tracktion.com/products/waveform-free">Tracktion Waveform</a> for the music.</p>

<p>I created some cool sounds effects for when the Gate closes, whenever a mob successfully passes through and when the Gate is destroyed (causing the player to immediately lose the game).</p>

<p>Every time a mob walks across the Gate a sound is played. In case it’s an Enemy then the sound effect that is played goes down in pitch, representing a bad action by the player. Whenever a Villager crosses, the sounds that is played goes up in pitch, positively reinforcing this action. This happens at the same time that the <strong>Morale</strong> bar updates on the top of the screen, which makes it a more coherent experience for the player.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/blog/posts/01-portcullis/part-4-chiptone.png" width="50%" /></p>

<p>I really enjoyed creating the sound effects with <strong>ChipTone</strong>. At a first glance one might think that you just need to press the Generator/Randomize buttons a couple of times and you’re done, but I actually spent more time fine-tuning each sound independently by playing with all the knobs and trying to understand how each one of the impacted the final result. Great piece of software!</p>

<p>I also planned on doing a background music loop. Nothing too fancy, just something that helped filling the void.
I ended up not doing it, so consequently I also didn’t have a chance of playing with <strong>Tracktion Waveform</strong>.
But as I said before, I have very convincing reason for it…</p>

<h3 id="the-twist">The Twist</h3>

<p>I caught Covid-19. I don’t know how. I don’t know why. It also doesn’t really matter.<br />
I’ve been feeling ill for almost a week now and I haven’t touched the game since. I’m not feeling terribly bad, but overall I’m lacking the concentration and enjoyment needed for working on the game.</p>

<p>It’s not an excuse. The game has, in my opinion, already surpassed any expectations that I had for a first project. But I still would have liked to work on it a little bit more. Instead, let’s take this extra motivation and use it for next month!</p>

<h3 id="thats-all-folks">That’s all Folks!</h3>

<p>One game, one month. One down, many more to go!</p>

<p>At the end of each month I will create a dedicated “Project” page to symbolize the launch of the game!<br />
The project page for this one lives here: <a href="/projects/gatekeeper">Gatekeeper</a>. Give it a look and, preferably, a play!</p>

<p>I’ll see you next month!</p>]]></content><author><name>dudezord</name><email>dudezord@protonmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If you haven’t yet, please read Part 1, Part 2 and Part 3.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/01-portcullis/part-4-finale.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/01-portcullis/part-4-finale.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Making my first game - Portcullis (Part 3)</title><link href="/blog/2022-04-19-making-my-first-game-portcullis-part-3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making my first game - Portcullis (Part 3)" /><published>2022-04-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-04-19T02:04:41+01:00</updated><id>/blog/making-my-first-game-portcullis-part-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2022-04-19-making-my-first-game-portcullis-part-3/"><![CDATA[<p class="note">If you haven’t yet, please read <a href="/blog/2022-04-01-making-my-first-game-portcullis-part-1">Part 1</a> and <a href="/blog/2022-04-09-making-my-first-game-portcullis-part-2">Part 2</a>.</p>

<ul id="markdown-toc">
  <li><a href="#hello-you-fine-folks" id="markdown-toc-hello-you-fine-folks">Hello, you fine folks!</a></li>
  <li><a href="#tasks" id="markdown-toc-tasks">Tasks</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#winning--losing-conditions" id="markdown-toc-winning--losing-conditions">Winning / Losing conditions</a></li>
      <li><a href="#game-art" id="markdown-toc-game-art">Game art</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#for-next-week" id="markdown-toc-for-next-week">For next week…</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#difficulty-tweaking" id="markdown-toc-difficulty-tweaking">Difficulty Tweaking</a></li>
      <li><a href="#game-art-1" id="markdown-toc-game-art-1">Game Art</a>        <ul>
          <li><a href="#enemy--villager" id="markdown-toc-enemy--villager">Enemy / Villager</a></li>
          <li><a href="#ui" id="markdown-toc-ui">UI</a></li>
          <li><a href="#sound-effects--music" id="markdown-toc-sound-effects--music">Sound effects / Music</a></li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="hello-you-fine-folks">Hello, you fine folks!</h2>

<p>Welcome to the 2nd development update of <strong>Gatekeeper</strong>.</p>

<p>If you recall, on the last post I wrote that this week I was going to implement the <strong>Winning/Losing</strong> conditions and work on the <strong>Game Art</strong>.</p>

<p>I was partial successful on both of them, so here’s what I have and haven’t done:</p>

<h2 id="tasks">Tasks</h2>

<h3 id="winning--losing-conditions">Winning / Losing conditions</h3>
<p>I used the concept of “points” that I presented last week and transformed it into a <strong>Morale</strong> meter.</p>

<p>Whenever the player kills an enemy or helps a fleeing villager, its morale increases.
If, otherwise, a villager is killed or an enemy enters the village, then the player’s morale decreases.</p>

<p>This translates directly to the overall game speed. A higher morale makes the game faster more prone to error, but also more engaging.
To add m a little bit more to the difficulty, I also added a Health meter to the gate. If the gate is closed but someone is being blocked by it, then the mob (villager or enemy) will start to damage the gate. This behaviour is to make sure that the player doesn’t try to stall the game, because a destroyed gate immediately loses the game.</p>

<p>The player will have 90 seconds to finish the game with the highest morale possible:</p>

<video controls="" loop="" src="/assets/img/blog/posts/01-portcullis/part-3-game-meters.mp4"></video>

<h3 id="game-art">Game art</h3>
<p>This was way more engaging than I previously antecipated. Although my lack of any type of arts and crafts skills, I think that I actually made some really good progress here.</p>

<p>I’ve been using <a href="https://www.aseprite.org/">Aseprite</a> so far, after watching a couple of basic tutorials. I had the <a href="https://www.aseprite.org/quickref/">cheatsheet</a> opened on my 2nd monitor, alongside with several reference images that I used for inspiration.</p>

<p>Currently, I’ve drawn the gate, the curtain walls that are on both sides and the grass where the mobs walk on.</p>

<p>I’ve enjoyed a lot the fast iteration between drawing and having the content immediately show on Godot.</p>

<p>Here’s a video with the current standing of the art:</p>
<video controls="" loop="" src="/assets/img/blog/posts/01-portcullis/part-3-game-art.mp4"></video>

<h2 id="for-next-week">For next week…</h2>

<h3 id="difficulty-tweaking">Difficulty Tweaking</h3>
<p>Although I already have a baseline difficulty scaling, I still didn’t fine-tune the different mechanic speeds as the morale increases. There are several things to consider: spawning rate, mob-type probability, movement speed and gate raising/lowering animations.</p>

<p>The main objective of this tweaking pass is to maximize engagement. The maximum morale should be possible to achieve on the last 15-30 seconds of the game, but should be hard to maintain. The game must also play smoothly and try not to be too repetitive (across several playthroughs).</p>

<h3 id="game-art-1">Game Art</h3>
<h4 id="enemy--villager">Enemy / Villager</h4>

<p>As can be seen of the previous video, I still didn’t draw the art for the enemies and villagers. Since these will require some sort of animation and will be a little bit more detailed than the rest of the art, I decided to postpone these to be the last art to be done.</p>

<h4 id="ui">UI</h4>

<p>I’m also missing some coherent UI to go along the pixel art. I plan to keep the “progress bar” meters for <strong>Morale</strong> and <strong>Gate Health</strong>, but I will need to play a little bit with their colors. I’ll also add a simple start an ending screens to tie everything together.</p>

<h4 id="sound-effects--music">Sound effects / Music</h4>

<p>I also plan to create some simple sound effects for when the gate closes or when a mob is killed. If I have time, I’ll try to come up with a simple music loop for the game.</p>

<p>Only a few days remaining until the end of the month. See you soon, for the final update on this project!</p>]]></content><author><name>dudezord</name><email>dudezord@protonmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If you haven’t yet, please read Part 1 and Part 2.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/01-portcullis/part-3.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/01-portcullis/part-3.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Making my first game - Portcullis (Part 2)</title><link href="/blog/2022-04-09-making-my-first-game-portcullis-part-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making my first game - Portcullis (Part 2)" /><published>2022-04-09T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-04-19T01:56:44+01:00</updated><id>/blog/making-my-first-game-portcullis-part-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2022-04-09-making-my-first-game-portcullis-part-2/"><![CDATA[<p class="note">If you haven’t yet, please read <a href="/blog/2022-04-01-making-my-first-game-portcullis-part-1">Part 1</a>.</p>

<ul id="markdown-toc">
  <li><a href="#hello-again" id="markdown-toc-hello-again">Hello, again!</a></li>
  <li><a href="#tasks" id="markdown-toc-tasks">Tasks</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#gate-placeholder" id="markdown-toc-gate-placeholder">Gate placeholder</a></li>
      <li><a href="#mobs-placeholder" id="markdown-toc-mobs-placeholder">Mobs placeholder</a></li>
      <li><a href="#simple-game-loop" id="markdown-toc-simple-game-loop">Simple game loop</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#until-next-week" id="markdown-toc-until-next-week">Until next week…</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#winning--losing-conditions" id="markdown-toc-winning--losing-conditions">Winning / Losing conditions</a></li>
      <li><a href="#game-art" id="markdown-toc-game-art">Game art</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="hello-again">Hello, again!</h2>

<p>A week has already passed, so it is time for an official™ update on the development of <strong>Gatekeeper</strong>.</p>

<p>I have been able to work a couple of hours each day on the project and I’m loving it! It has been pretty cool so far to learn Godot as it is pretty beginner-friendly on how to make things.</p>

<p>The first few days I dedicated to go through <a href="https://docs.godotengine.org/en/stable/getting_started/introduction/index.html">some tutorials</a> to learn the basics of Godot.</p>

<p>After I felt I knew the bare minimum to start programming this game, I jumped directly into it.
The first task was to create a placeholder for the most important element of the game… the <strong>Gate</strong>.</p>

<h2 id="tasks">Tasks</h2>

<h3 id="gate-placeholder">Gate placeholder</h3>
<p>I started by mocking up an isometric shape, since I thought it would give more depth and character to the gate than a simple 2D side-view.
I immediatelly put my hands on creating a raise and lower animations that felt somewhat convincing. This was pretty easy to do, thanks to the usage of Ease functions on Godot animations.
<br /></p>

<video style="vertical-align: middle;" controls="" loop="" src="/assets/img/blog/posts/01-portcullis/part-2-Gate_Animation.mp4"></video>

<p><br />
Afterwards, I decided that the gate would have two collision areas:</p>
<ul>
  <li>a side one, which would behave like a wall to stop mobs;</li>
  <li>a bottom one, which would behave like the area with spikes that will kill the enemies.</li>
</ul>

<p>In the end, I ended up with the best gate I have ever made in my life. Behold!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/img/blog/posts/01-portcullis/part-2-gate-placeholder.jpg" /></p>

<h3 id="mobs-placeholder">Mobs placeholder</h3>

<p>Having extensive experience developing Gate placeholders made creating the mobs placeholder very easy.
Mobs also have two collision areas:</p>
<ul>
  <li>one for stopping when they reach the closed gate;</li>
  <li>another for detecting when they are being smashed by the gate.</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="/assets/img/blog/posts/01-portcullis/part-2-mob-placeholder.jpg" /></p>

<h3 id="simple-game-loop">Simple game loop</h3>

<p>Now it was finally time to start gluing things together.</p>

<p>I created a basic Spawner script to randomly spawn villagers or enemies.
These would walk automatically towards the Gate, and would either collide with it or pass through.</p>

<p>Collisions use four separate Physics Layers to detect which part of the mob collided with which part of the gate.
Each collision with the gate triggers a separate area_entered() signal, depending if it collided with the side or the bottom part.
A new signal is then emited to the colliding mob, telling them to “stop” or “die”.
If the gate raises then they are no longer colliding, so a “move” signal is emited from the Gate to the mob.</p>

<p>A corresponding Despawner script was also added to make sure the mobs can graciously be terminated once they leave the screen.</p>

<p>You can see it all in action below.</p>

<video controls="" loop="" src="/assets/img/blog/posts/01-portcullis/part-2-Game_Loop.mp4"></video>

<p class="note" title="A poem">Villagers are green,<br />
EnemySoliders are red,<br />
don’t walk near a falling gate,<br />
or you will end up dead!</p>

<h2 id="until-next-week">Until next week…</h2>
<p>These are the tasks that I will attempt to work on for the following week:</p>

<h3 id="winning--losing-conditions">Winning / Losing conditions</h3>
<p>Having already a basic game loop, my next task will be implementing the core losing/winning conditions for the game. My current concept is to award points whenever the player kills an enemy or lets a villager through, and deduct points otherwise.</p>

<p>I also though about relating the spawning/movement rate of the mobs and movement speed of the gate with the overall success rate of the player. The better the player, the faster the game gets, the more points are available to earn.</p>

<p>After a set amount of time, the game ends, and the player receives its final score.</p>

<h3 id="game-art">Game art</h3>
<p>Now, this is where my vulnerabilities start. Let me begin by assuring you that I was never good at drawing. I don’t even consider myself mediocre. I consciously avoided any kind of arts and crafts project since I was a kid.</p>

<p>I already got some motivation by watching a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rXuR78-IJ9Y">great video</a> of another fellow game developer. Make sure to <a href="https://www.twitch.tv/jotson">follow</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/yafd">him</a>, because he works on really cool stuff.</p>

<div class="sixteen-nine">
<iframe style="width:100%;height:100%;" width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rXuR78-IJ9Y" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<p><br />
<br />
With that in mind, I’ll give it my absolute best.<br />
I’ll see you again in about a week, with another development update.</p>]]></content><author><name>dudezord</name><email>dudezord@protonmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If you haven’t yet, please read Part 1.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/01-portcullis/part-2.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/01-portcullis/part-2.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Making my first game - Portcullis (Part 1)</title><link href="/blog/2022-04-01-making-my-first-game-portcullis-part-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making my first game - Portcullis (Part 1)" /><published>2022-04-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-03-31T01:08:17+01:00</updated><id>/blog/making-my-first-game-portcullis-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2022-04-01-making-my-first-game-portcullis-part-1/"><![CDATA[<ul id="markdown-toc">
  <li><a href="#greetings-fellow-adventurer" id="markdown-toc-greetings-fellow-adventurer">Greetings, fellow adventurer!</a></li>
  <li><a href="#theme---portcullis" id="markdown-toc-theme---portcullis">Theme - “Portcullis”</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#definition" id="markdown-toc-definition">Definition</a></li>
      <li><a href="#initial-ideas" id="markdown-toc-initial-ideas">Initial ideas</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#game-concept---gatekeeper" id="markdown-toc-game-concept---gatekeeper">Game Concept - “Gatekeeper”</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="greetings-fellow-adventurer">Greetings, fellow adventurer!</h2>

<p>The time has come for my first challenge.
As you <a href="/blog/2022-03-02-the-plan-is-simple/" class="external">already know</a>, I will be doing one game a month as a way to learn everything I can about game development.</p>

<p>Starting from now (April 2022), every month I will make a game from start-to-finish based on one of the original themes of <a href="/projects/1GAM">#1GAM</a>.</p>

<p>With that in mind, the theme for this month is… <em>**drum roll**</em></p>

<h2 id="theme---portcullis">Theme - “Portcullis”</h2>

<p>Before we proceed, I suggest you listen to the <a href="/projects/1GAM/#1">original keynote</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/McFunkypants">@McFunkypants</a>.<br />
His words convey all the meaning that I want this blog to have.<br />
For lots of current game developers, their journey started there and then. For me, it (re-)starts now.<br /></p>

<p>With that in mind, let’s begin!</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <h3 id="definition">Definition</h3>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portcullis">Portcullis</a> is the name given to a defensive sliding gate at the entrance of a castle. It is mounted on vertical grooves and can be raised and lowered very rapidly by a single guard. It can be used to prevent the passage of unwanted enemies, or even to trap them between two consecutive portcullises.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <h3 id="initial-ideas">Initial ideas</h3>
    <p>The first game ideas that came to my mind were:</p>
    <ul>
      <li><strong>“Gatekeeper”</strong> - You guard the main gate of your medieval city. You have to decide who enters and who can leave. Good choices might have good consequences. Bad choices will always prove to be bad.</li>
      <li><strong>“Open the gate!”</strong> - The King and Queen have returned from their long vacation, but it looks like they lost the keys to the Castle. You, as the Official Lockpicker of the Reign, shall open the gate for their Royal Highnesses. But don’t take too long, or you might lose your head.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>I decided to go with <strong>“Gatekeeper”</strong> as I was having some issues coming up with puzzles/mechanics for the other title.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="game-concept---gatekeeper">Game Concept - “Gatekeeper”</h2>
<p>In this game, you play the very important role of guarding the entrance to the city.<br />
As a core mechanic, you will have the ability of lowering and raising the Portcullis.</p>

<p>You might allow your citizens to enter, while prohibiting undesired people from doing the same.
When enemies come to attack, you will be able to use the spikes of the falling Portcullis to crush them and prevent their success.</p>

<p>Do a good enough of a job and you will be able to upgrade your abilities in defending the Kingdom.<br />
Do a bad enough of a job and it will be your head on a spike instead!</p>

<p><br />
<br />
Time to finally get my hands dirty and play with <a href="https://godotengine.org">Godot</a> for the first time.<br />
I’ll be back next week, with an update on the development of this project. See you soon!</p>]]></content><author><name>dudezord</name><email>dudezord@protonmail.com</email></author><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/01-portcullis/part-1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/01-portcullis/part-1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The plan is simple</title><link href="/blog/2022-03-02-the-plan-is-simple/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The plan is simple" /><published>2022-03-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-31T01:08:18+01:00</updated><id>/blog/the-plan-is-simple</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2022-03-02-the-plan-is-simple/"><![CDATA[<p class="note">If you haven’t read my <a href="/blog/2022-03-01-a-new-beginning">initial blog post</a>, please check it first!</p>

<ul id="markdown-toc">
  <li><a href="#the-plan-is-simple" id="markdown-toc-the-plan-is-simple">The plan is simple</a></li>
  <li><a href="#or-is-it" id="markdown-toc-or-is-it">Or is it?</a></li>
  <li><a href="#ready-set" id="markdown-toc-ready-set">Ready? Set…</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-plan-is-simple">The plan is simple</h2>

<p>I already have some definitive ideas about what I want to do:</p>
<ul>
  <li>All the programming will be done on <a href="https://godotengine.org"><strong>Godot</strong></a>. I only have a little bit of experience using other engines, but since Godot is the <em>“new”</em> cool kid on the block, I decided on it.</li>
  <li>Project ideas will come sequentially from the amazing list of <a href="/projects/1GAM"><strong>#1GAM</strong></a>. I compiled the entire list of themes and keynotes since they aren’t available on the original site anymore.</li>
  <li>On each project, I will focus on improving one or more parts of game development where I don’t feel as confident. This can be anything from planning, writing, coding, art, modelling, music, marketing, setting up a Steam page, etc. 
<br />I only ever did <strong>programming</strong> since 2008, so the opportunities to learn the remaining stuff are endless.</li>
  <li>Regarding <em>deadlines</em>, I intend to honor the <a href="/projects/1GAM"><strong>#1GAM</strong></a> motto - one game a month.</li>
  <li>Document everything! This is a learning experiment, both for you and me. Even a website/blog is something I never did in the past. We are already making progress! 😄</li>
  <li>… and most important, <strong>ENJOY</strong> the journey!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="or-is-it">Or is it?</h2>

<p>I still don’t know what software I’ll use for practicing all the other stuff. I also don’t know how frequently I should write updates on my progress.
<br />
I’ll gladly take suggestions from the audience.</p>

<h2 id="ready-set">Ready? Set…</h2>
<p>I guess we will have to see how it goes!</p>]]></content><author><name>dudezord</name><email>dudezord@protonmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If you haven’t read my initial blog post, please check it first!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/solo-developers.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/solo-developers.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A new beginning</title><link href="/blog/2022-03-01-a-new-beginning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A new beginning" /><published>2022-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-31T01:08:19+01:00</updated><id>/blog/a-new-beginning</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2022-03-01-a-new-beginning/"><![CDATA[<ul id="markdown-toc">
  <li><a href="#hello-everyone" id="markdown-toc-hello-everyone">Hello everyone!</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="hello-everyone">Hello everyone!</h2>
<p><br />
My real name is Pedro and I was born in the beautiful and sunny 🇵🇹 Portugal.
<br />
Since I was a young child that I had the desire to one day become a Game Developer.</p>

<p>At 18 years of age, I started to pursue my dream and enrolled in a Computer Science degree.
<br />
At 26 years of age, I finished my MSc in Graphics Programming and Game Development.</p>

<p>I was ready. The World was ready. The time had come. Right? <em>Right…?!?!</em></p>

<p>5 years have already passed and the answer is: <strong>WRONG</strong>!</p>

<p>I was never able to work on games professionally.
<br />
And because of that I also never had the motivation to work on them on my free time.</p>

<p>The time has finally come… The journey starts now!</p>]]></content><author><name>dudezord</name><email>dudezord@protonmail.com</email></author><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/press-start.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/assets/img/blog/posts/press-start.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>